<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Musings of J. Kessa Roberts</title>
    <description>Kessa Roberts is a doctoral student in Educational Policy at The Ohio State University. Her intersts include parental involvement &amp; rural education.
</description>
    <link>http://kessaroberts.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://kessaroberts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 23:28:48 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 23:28:48 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Power of Parental Involvement Policies to Increase Educational Inequity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite two decades worth of educational policy that have emphasized the role of the parent in a child’s academic achievement, neither researchers nor policymakers have critically analyzed the current parental involvement policies to determine their impact on educational inequality. Unfortunately, the parental involvement policy in Title I of No Child Left Behind is not an exception to this lack of critical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title I is a piece of the No Child Left Behind legislation that aims to improve educational outcomes for children in high-need schools. Title I funds are allocated to schools based on the school’s percentage from low-income families. Title I is the nation’s largest education program, serving more than 21 million children during the 2009-2010 school year with appropriations of over $14 billion in 2011 (U.S. Department of Education, 2014). The parental involvement section of Title I aims to increase&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in large part on how parental involvement is defined and measured, results from parental involvement studies vary but overall they demonstrate that parental involvement has a positive effect on a child’s academic achievement. What research has also demonstrated is that parents are not involved in their children’s education at the same rates or in the same ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite an overall increase in parental involvement after NCLB was implemented (see Figure 1 below), discrepancies in parental involvement rates persist with white, middle-class parents involved at higher rates than minority parents. In addition, highly educated parents are involved at the school site at drastically larger rates than parents with less formal education (see Figure 2 below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;figure-1&quot;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/a1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;figure-2&quot;&gt;Figure 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/a2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the current Title I parental involvement policy is twofold. First, the language of the policy focuses on parental involvement in ways that often align with middle-class expectations for such involvement. Secondly, the policy does not adequately address the barriers that minority parents and parents of lower socioeconomic status face. By valuing activities like attending meetings and monitoring homework rather than a broad range of activities often endorsed by minority and parents of lower socioeconomic status, these parents are disenfranchised and are not considered meaningful partners in their children’s education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disenfranchisement will likely perpetuate the very cycles of educational inequity that Title 1 aims to ameliorate. In order to address this inequity, the language of the policy must be rewritten to encompass a broader conceptualization of parental involvement. In this way, schools will be encouraged to view parental involvement in a manner that values the unique perspectives of each parent resulting in meaningful initiatives that encourage involvement from all parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more information on the data images presented in this post, please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.childtrends.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/39_Parent_Involvement_In_Schools.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.childtrends.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/39_Parent_Involvement_In_Schools.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 10:54:09 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://kessaroberts.github.io/parental/involvement/2015/04/29/the-power-of-parental-involvement-policies-to-increase-educational-inequity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kessaroberts.github.io/parental/involvement/2015/04/29/the-power-of-parental-involvement-policies-to-increase-educational-inequity.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>parental</category>
        
        <category>involvement</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
